Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For all the lovers in the world,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
I was going to pay respect to the Empress after greeting Consort Fleur.
Will you make way for me?
Lunar, Attendant Yu will go first.
Let's go.
She just became a Companion.
Who does she think she is?
A maid does not speak of a concubine like that.
I will not do it again.
The more you talk about her, the more trouble you will get.
"Forbearance calms a stormy sea."
Yes.
Let's go.
Ying'er entertained Mother by the opera Together Forever yesterday.
I wish to give her the alias Lady Melodic.
What do you think?
A reputation well deserved.
Your Majesty, it's time to select a concubine.
I was told that not every concubine has served you.
Attendant Sourire has been sick.
Attendant Chun is too young.
Is there anyone else?
Yes, Companion An.
Companion An it is.
My Lady, you're back!
I've been looking for you.
Where did you go?
Where else can I go? I was visiting Lady Shen.
The greenhouse kept saying that the narcissi are difficult to grow.
Why do we have so many today?
Congratulations, My Lady!
The Attendant Services informed us
that you will serve His Majesty tonight.
What?
It's your big day, My Lady!
So many flowers were sent when the news arrived.
The Imperial Kitchen sent you Shandong Ejiao.
[gelatin from donkey skin made in Shangdong Province]
It's about time. Let me help you get ready.
I thought His Majesty didn't even remember me.
[No, he didn't.]
Don't worry, My Lady.
His Majesty is still working. He'll be a bit late.
Later, the servants will carry you into his palace.
You'll wait for His Majesty in bed.
What's wrong, My Lady?
Madam, I feel scared somehow.
It's going to be fine.
What is wrong?
I ... I ...
I'm not that scary. Did the madam tell you the rules?
I don't like to force anyone. Maybe next time.
Su Peisheng.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Take her away.
Call for Companion Yu.
Yes.
What bad luck! I've never run such an errand.
A concubine carried in and returned untouched.
Who is singing at this time of the night?
It must be Lady Melodic.
It is inappropriate to sing loudly late at night.
Nevertheless, it's good for His Majesty
to have a lively mind after a busy day.
Is there a Lady Shen?
Yes, from the Concubine Selection.
She's gentle and sensible.
That is what the emperor needs.
The Empress is taking good care of the harem.
There's nothing to worry about.
He is the only son I have.
But now he has so many concubines.
I have to keep a watch in case they get out of line.
I heard that His Majesty loves your Kungqu.
It puts his mind at ease after a day's work.
No wonder His Majesty is very fond of you.
What songs do you sing?
I learned The Peony Pavilion from my father.
Do you know the song "A Gem Intactly Returned"?
Only Companion An can sing that song to the fullest.
The Empress tried really hard, only to make a fool of herself.
Wrinkles furrow her disappointed face,
while vigor and radiance shine on Your Highness's.
That is very sweet of you.
My brother had this face massager sent to me.
It is made of the finest jade.
It keeps your skin young.
I'll let you have it.
I thank Your Highness.
Companion An is doomed.
She came from nothing and His Majesty doesn't like her.
Were I sent out of the Palace of Mental Cultivation like her,
I would never let people see me again.
But she's acting like nothing happened.
Servants must not talk about a concubine behind her back.
I'll ask Her Majesty to expel you
from the palace if you do this again.
Is that clear?
Yes, My Lady. I'm sorry.
Peace to Lady Shen. Peace to Attendant Sourire.
- Greetings.
- Please sit.
How are you doing?
I'm fine. Thank you both for coming.
You have another chance in the future.
We have a long future ahead of us.
You both have a future, but I don't.
My Lady, it is still cold at night in February.
It's been even colder than January lately.
You have been doing needlework all day.
Here, keep your hands warm.
The Household Department did not provide enough
winter clothes. We have to make clothes by ourselves.
When I sent the patries to Companion An at noon,
I saw them doing needlework too.
They said the eunuchs will trade the clothes
for money outside the palace.
Compared to Companion An,
why is Companion Yu living it up?
Don't talk about concubines behind their back.
Meizhuang told me that His Majesty is
cutting the spending in the harem.
Every palace is doing needlework to make ends meet.
We are not short of money right now.
Jade, bring some money to Companion An tomorrow.
They'll need that for spring clothing.
Who is it at this time?
Go check out.
Attendant Chun! Why are you here by yourself?
Come on in.
My Lady, it's Attendant Chun.
Chun'er, what is wrong?
- I was so scared.
- Calm down.
Bring a cup of milk tea.
I'm right here.
Don't cry.
The milk tea is coming.
It's all right.
Here.
I was walking with Attendant Joie.
One lantern caught fire and started to burn.
Companion Yu happened to be passing by.
The fire startled the horse pulling her carriage.
I saw it very clear that the horse was well trained.
It only causes a minor bump.
Companion Yu came on strong,
and Attendant Joie wasn't very friendly.
Attendant Joie has been a concubine for longer
and at a higher rank than Companion Yu.
She doesn't need to be too respectful to a Companion.
But Companion Yu is adored by
His Majesty and backed by Concort Fleur.
Attendant Joie has been uncomfortable about that.
They had a fight.
Companion Yu had Attendant Joie sent to
the Department of Penalty in a huff.
The Department of Penalty?
That is the jailhouse for servants.
How can Attendant Joie be sent there?
Were His Majesty and Her Majesty informed?
Companion Yu said she will hold responsible
the head of the department if His Majesty is disturbed.
I've never heard of such a ridiculous thing.
Sourire, what should we do now?
Don't worry.
Xiao-Yunzi.
Xiao-Yunzi will walk with you to your palace.
I will talk to Meizhuang tomorrow.
She'll report to the Empress.
Xiao-Yunzi,
please go with her.
I feel sorry for her
that she has to live in terror at such a young age.
Attendants can even be bullied by a Companion.
Life is miserable without His Majesty's fondness.
Yu sings late at night and punishes concubines at will.
This might turn out to be a good thing.
How so?
Her sudden advancement has been a thorn in many concubines' flesh.
Her reckless behavior will dig her own grave.
You are the only carefree person today.
The palace was turned upside town.
What happened?
The Empress Dowager made an edict to release and console Attendant Joie,
and to deprive Companion Yu of her alias and confine her for 15 days.
By the Empress Dowager?
Yes.
Why not by His Majesty or the Empress?
His Majesty is too busy with the state affairs.
The Empress was visiting the Empress Dowager and informed her.
Her Majesty is very lenient.
I hope Companion Yu has leaned her lesson.
While Yu is still ranked at Companion,
her status is affected for losing her alias.
(pleasant)
The brush writes smoothly today.
I'll keep this one.
Now that Yu is quelled, Your Majesty can write in peace.
The Empress Dowager is very supportive of Your Majesty.
His Majesty would be partial to her
if I made the edict to punish his new favorite.
Instead of balancing his authority and mine,
I had the most effective solution given by the Empress Dowager.
That was a brilliant idea!
The weather has been better lately.
You look healthier as you lower the dosage.
It's fine to stop taking the medicine if everything goes right.
Since you have recovered,
we can go outside often and get more sunlight.
It's good for your skin.
You wanted to have a swing put up in the garden.
Xiao-Yunzi built one.
It is surrounded by apricot flowers.
Would you like to go check out?
"In the moving shadows of apricot flowers,
I play the flute till the first light appears."
You guys have a million ways to get me out the doors.
I'll go then.
- Vermilion, get me my flute.
- Go.
How may I address Your Excellency?
Hmm?
Can you guess?
Are you the emperor?
You are a prince?
Have you heard of Noble Prince Guo?
Are you Noble Prince Guo?
Have you seen me ... before?
No, I did not even see His Majesty after I moved in.
So why did you think that I'm not?
You don't look his age ...
A man doesn't always look his age.
If you say so.
I am the Attendant from the Zhen family.
Peace to Your Lordship.
You are the Attendant who has long been sick?
How did Your Lordship know such a trifle in the harem?
I heard it from the Empress.
The emperor asked about you at the new year banquet.
I overhead it.
I see.
Are you feeling better?
You should have put on a coat outdoors.
Thank you for asking.
I've been feeling much better.
Vermilion, this is Noble Prince Guo.
Peace to Your Lordship.
I heard you playing "The Flying Apricot Petals".
It is an appropriate song for the garden right now.
Is Your Lordship familiar with the song?
The song will sound even more peaceful
if you play it with Xun [globular flute] on a spring night.
But Xiao [end-blown flute] made it more uplifting.
It feels like wind clearing the ground snow.
I'm not a good player.
Thank you for bearing with my playing.
You were playing it very well.
But when you were playing the line
"Fragrant spring grass carpeting the shore,
no further to home can I go towards."
the music sounded like a stifled sob.
Do you miss home?
“Zhou Yu would notice even the smallest mistake of the musicians.”
Your Lordship is even better than him.
It's been long since I heard such beautiful flute music.
Since Empress Première passed away.
I am deeply flattered.
I dare not compare myself to Empress Première.
I should go back to my palace now.
- I bid Your Lordship a good day.
- Sure.
My Lady.
Violet.
Can you ask around if Noble Prince Guo came to the palace today?
Do you not believe he is Noble Prince Guo?
What do you think?
We can never be too careful.
Peace to Your Majesty.
- Rise.
- Thank you.
Why are you here so early?
I could afford no delay when I heard that
you got an authentic painting of Wu Daozi.
I can't wait to see it.
Why? The painting doesn't run.
A famous painting is like a beautiful woman.
You have to see it as soon as possible.
But you haven't married any beautiful woman yet.
I was hoping to, but I changed my mind
after seeing the one crying outside your palace.
- Su Peisheng.
- Your Majesty.
Was Yu here?
Yes, she came here very early.
She requested to see Your Majesty in tears.
She kept crying for quite a while before she left.
That's okay.
I remember that I have a flute made of Lantian Jade.
Go get it for me.
Where did you go?
I was visiting Mother.
And I took a walk in the garden.
Sorry that you had to see a crying woman alone.
How does Your Majesty like the lady from the leaning plum trees?
Just fine. Not as adorable as she was that night.
Your mind's eye saw better than your eyes.
Let's go see the painting.
My Lady, Noble Prince Guo is in the palace.
He is admiring paintings with His Majesty.
I hear that he looks older than his age, as if he is 40.
That's not true. He was born in the 35th Year, Kangxi Reign.
He's about 25 years old this year.
State Prince Heng is in his 40s.
He is easy-going and fond of talking to us.
What about His Majesty?
I have no idea.
His Majesty doesn't come to the harem a lot.
And he's always followed by a mass of servants.
I am too humble to see His Majesty.
That's true. His Majesty is always followed by servants.
You're good to go.
I'm sorry for what you are going through.
But there's nothing His Majesty can do
about the Empress Dowager's edict.
Her Majesty is known for her mildest temper in the palace.
But she was very strict with the careless slip I made.
Someone else must be fanning the flames.
Whether it was Her Majesty's decision or not,
your 15-day confinement is over.
There's nothing else she can do.
But ... But His Majesty is not willing to see me.
(sigh) True. I'm afraid he will forget you after some time.
Your Highness, please help me!
I don't want to be neglected in the palace,
or be sent back to work in the garden.
Your Highness.
It is His Majesty that you wish to see.
You should help yourself to make him see you.
"A request made in person is hard to turn down."
But ... But I don't know what to do.
Do what you're good at doing.
I thank Your Highness for your advice.
Song Zhi, walk Companion Yu out.
My Lady.
His Majesty was very fond of Companion Yu.
Why would Your Highness help someone
who would compete with you?
It was the Empress Doager who punished her,
rather than His Majesty.
I helped her in case His Majesty thinks of her some day.
She will be able to balance with Lady Shen for me.
Your Highness, Lady Shen is new to the palace.
Why would you mind her?
She was allowed to learn about housekeeping as a new concubine.
That is why.
Stop. You guys go without me.
I'll take a walk by myself.
But Her Majesty told me to look after Your Majesty.
I'll be dead if I don't follow you.
You'll be dead if you do.
Put it down.
Don't tell anyone.
Let's go.
You wanna go higher?
Just a bit.
I know you're afraid.
It'll be my turn to push later.
Sure, I'm not afraid of height.
Vermilion, don't play tricks on me.
Your Lordship!
Get down if you're scared.
I'm not. Your Lordship can keep pushing.
A bit higher.
And higher.
My Lady.
Greetings.
My Lady, are you all right?
Now you're scared.
You were acting brave just now.
Apologies for my manners.
I didn't know Your Lordship would sneak behind my back.
Are you blaming my manners?
I was passing by the garden.
It reminded me of the song you played
and I thought you might be playing the flute here.
But I do not have the flute with me today.
I'll have to come another time.
There are many apricot flowers here.
The song you played is also about the flowers.
Is it because you like apricot flowers?
Apricot is not as bright as peach, or cold as plum.
It is modest and gentle.
People and flowers are alike.
Only a modest and gentle person can be attracted to the flowers alike.
But I don't really like apricot flowers.
Why is that?
Despite its beautiful flowers,
apricot is sour and the seeds are bitter.
Life would be meaningless if it begins well but ends badly.
I'd rather have an evergreen life like pine and cypress,
not blooming or bearing fruits.
I've never heard of such a curious point of view.
I was talking nonsense.
Hope Your Lordship can excuse me.
I apologize for being rude.
I have two scores of flute music.
I wish to show them to you at this hour five days later.
I hope you would like to be here for them.
I'm honored to obey.
May I trouble Your Lordship for a favor?
Go ahead.
It is inappropriate for me to meet Your Lordship privately.
I hope no one else would know and blemish our reputation.
Why would they blemish our reputation?
Your Lordship and I are above board,
but gossip can spread widely in the harem.
I wish not to bring us any trouble.
Certainly.
I thank Your Lordship.
Who is it?
What happened, My Lady?
I'm not seeing anyone.
We live in two different worlds.
What's this poem about husband all about?
[The Book of Songs]
My Lady should take a break if you're tired from reading.
The paint on the table came off.
When will the Household Department have it fixed.
Xiao-Yunzi has requested for maintenance.
They will send someone to fix it soon.
Your Majesty, please take a break.
Why did Your Majesty stop?
I'm all ears.
I can't play the flute very well.
Empress Première was the best flute player in the palace.
Now we have another one.
Is Your Majesty talking about Prince XVII?
His Lordship is best at playing the flute.
- Su Peisheng.
-Yes
Send for Prince XVII.
You've been away the whole afternoon.
Why are you back with a sad face?
I went to the Household Department.
They could have talked more nicely.
You were just requesting for some paint, not the stipend.
Why did you get nothing after a few trips?
Since Consort Fleur is in charge of the harem,
those snobbish servants look down upon our palace.
I'm fine with what they said about me,
but they even badmouthed My Lady.
They made offensive remarks.
How dare those bastards?
They bullied us on charcoal, and now the paint.
Shh, My Lady is inside.
She will feel bad if she hears it.
What should we do?
We servants can get by.
How can My Lady live with that?
Huang Guiquan is such a bully under his relative Consort Feaur's wing.
My goodness, please keep it down.
I'm begging of you.
I can make do with the table
if the Household Department is busy.
It's no big deal.
You and I heard nothing.
Don't blame them.
It must have been difficult for you all
to serve a concubine like me.
Why would you say that, My Lady?
I'm terribly flattered.
I never feel negative about serving you.
In a palace full of snobs,
I am nobody as a useless concubine.
You must have heard such good flute music
that you can't put the flute away.
You've been listening to all the flute players in the palace.
That's just like scratching the boot for an itching foot.
Is it that difficult to satisfy you?
I wonder what she looks like.
You are rotten to the bone.
My Lady, His Majesty does not see concubines
as he's talking to Noble Prince Guo.
You've been saying that for days.
I am no fool.
I am telling you the truth.
There's nothing I can do if you don't trust me.
I'd like to bother you to inform His Majesty.
I have told you that
His Majesty does not see concubines
as he's talking to Noble Prince Guo.
Why would you make it difficult for us servants?
I heard that Companion Yu kneeled for half a night.
That made His Majesty's heart soft.
Not the kneeling. It was her songs.
Now she's having a sore throat.
Nevertheless, she's back.
Look at that.
She was just a maid like us.
She sang her way to be a mistress,
while we got eyes rolling at us when we claim stipend.
The same beginning can turn into different endings.
She's not even as pretty as you are.
Nonsense.
Xiao-Xiazi, come here.
Yes, My Lady.
Shell the walnuts for me since you have nothing to do.
With your hands.
My Lady, I'm afraid
I can't shell them even until my hands crack.
Now you are work-shy?
You've been a diligent servant to His Majesty.
When His Majesty feels like walnut,
what's the big deal about cracking your hands.
Xiao-Xiazi, what time is it?
It's 1:30 pm.
Idiot! You should have awaken me!
But Your Majesty always sleeps until this time.
Slap yourself.
Get the coat, the coat!
Your Majesty.
You dork!
How could you forget His Majesty's
time to rise because of the walnuts?
Look at your hands.
How are you going to work for the rest of the day?
It's okay, go.
I'm taking a walk.
But it's raining outside.
That's why I walk.
You can leave.
- Your Majesty.
- Stop.
The Empress Dowager wishes to see you right now.
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.